Okay, so in this video then, we are going
to cover another very, very important
tool, another very important term called
reserve analysis.
Okay, so let's go straight into reserve
analysis.
Now reserve analysis is actually a risk
management term.
This is covered in risk management,
but even before we get to risk management,
this is a term or this is a tool that is
impacting several areas.
It's impacting the cost, it's impacting
the schedule, it's impacting resources.
Remember, a risk is
a major constraint on a
project and it impacts
every area of the project.
And this particular term then, or this
particular tool is known
as reserve analysis.
All right, so let's talk about this in
detail.
So there's two types of risk reserves that
you need to be aware of.
You've got something
called the contingency
reserve, something called
the management reserve.
Contingency reserves basically relate to
money that you have
set aside for known risks.
Known risks.
And a risk is an unknown.
A risk is it may or may not happen.
So that's where you get this term called
known unknowns.
It's a known unknown unknown.
We've identified that it could happen but
we don't know if it will happen.
And so we as project managers are
responsible for that.
Senior management, on the other hand,
are going to look at the project overall,
determine this is a high-risk project,
medium risk, low-risk, that kind of thing.
And they're going to put some money aside
for complete unknown eventualities.
Unknown risks.
Unknown unknowns.
Again, a risk is an unknown.
own.
And that is management's responsibility.
So project managers are responsible for
contingency reserves.
They are not responsible for management
reserves.
Okay.
All right, so let's just give you a very
simple example there.
So let's say there's the, there is a risk
that material prices may increase,
right?
We're, you know, reading the news or we're
looking at the news and seeing that,
you know, something is happening and
material prices may start increasing.
It may happen, it may not happen.
We don't know if it will happen.
We don't know if material
prices will start increasing,
but we've heard that
they might start increasing.
So we've identified this, so it's known,
but we don't know if
it will happen or not.
So it's a known risk, it's a known
unknown.
So if material prices
start increasing, then that's
going to have a financial
impact on our project.
So we've identified that we, meaning the
project manager, we as project managers
have identified that this is a potential
for something to happen on our project.
This is a risk in our project.
It may happen, it may not happen.
We might end up having
to spend more money on
materials, right, because
of the price increase.
So we're going to determine what's the
probability of that happening,
what's impact of it
happening, again, which
we'll cover in the risk
management section.
And then we're going
to put some money aside
in contingency reserves
in case that happens.
But we don't know
if it will, but we've got
some money in contingency
reserves just in case.
So that is a known risk, a known unknown.
And we as project managers are
responsible.
Now, senior management then are going to
be looking at this project overall.
and they're going to determine high risk,
medium risk, low risk what happens if just
something happens and it's beyond
anybody's control so they may set some
money aside in what's known as management
reserves for complete unknown
eventualities we didn't identify it we
couldn't have identified it so it's an
unknown risk or an unknown unknown and
that's senior management's responsibility
So as a very simple example, this whole
COVID situation.
Right.
So at the beginning of 2020, we didn't
know about the COVID situation.
We didn't know how it was going to be
impacted.
So all of a sudden though, it impacted the
whole world.
Pretty much the whole world almost came to
a standstill.
Impacted many, many projects.
now project managers wouldn't have been
responsible for identifying that the
project manager couldn't identify that
that's just something that happened we had
no control over it that's just something
that happened so any projects that got put
on hold any projects where the cost
suddenly increased right or projects
obviously failed many projects failed at
that point right because because of the
whole COVID that's not the
project manager's responsibility
that would be senior
management's responsibility.
So any money from that would have come
from the management reserves.
Unknown risks or complete unknown
unknowns.
And best way to think of management reserves
is, think of it as a rainy day fund.
We're not going to touch it unless we
absolutely have to.
Now, senior management are responsible for
management reserves.
The project manager is not responsible for
Most of the time, project managers have no
idea how much is the management reserves,
right?
They are only responsible for contingency
reserve.
And so the cost baseline, right,
which is covered in a separate video,
but the cost baseline,
which is the project manager's
budget, that includes
the contingency reserve.
That does not include the management
reserves.
Okay.
Now, these contingency and management
reserves is not just in terms of cost.
Remember, risks impact all areas of the
project.
It could also be in terms of, for example,
the schedule.
So we've identified a risk, let's say,
vendor may delay shipment of raw materials.
It may or may not have a financial impact.
If it has a financial
impact, we're going to
put some money aside
in contingency reserves.
Right, but it may not have financial
impact or additionally there may be a
scheduling impact it may delay the if
they're delay in shipment of raw materials
that may have a scheduling impact on our
project so if we've identified this in
advance we might put in some duration
buffers right into our schedule right and
the management themselves they may extend
the timeline based on some complete
unknowns again because this COVID
situation many projects were put on hold
They might not have been cancelled, but
they've been put on
hold until a future date.
So project managers wouldn't have been
responsible for identifying that.
Senior management would be responsible for
that.
So again, reserve analysis then.
It could be in terms of cost.
It could be in terms of schedule.
It could also be in terms of resources
because it impacts many
areas of your project.
Now, if they ever ask you to do any
calculations on reserve analysis,
and we are going to be
covering some calculations
on this in the risk management section.
We're going to be covering EMV,
expected monetary value.
So if they're ever asking
you to do any calculations,
then generally it will be
from a monetary perspective.
But just no contingency
reserves could be from a
monetary perspective or
a scheduling perspective.
It could even be from a resource
perspective as well.